Hi, my name is David Brown, and this is a reading writing class.
안녕하세요, 제 이름은 데이비드 브라운입니다. 본 수업은 읽기 쓰기 수업입니다.
Hello, welcome. How are you?
안녕하세요, 환영합니다. 오늘 어떠신가요?
Hi, nice to meet you.
네, 만나서 반갑습니다.
Nice to meet you too. My name is David. What's your name?
저도 만나서 반갑습니다. 제 이름은 데이비드입니다. 성함이 어떻게 되시죠?
My name is Francesco. Pleasure to meet you, David.
제 이름은 프란체스코입니다. 만나서 반갑습니다, 데이비드 선생님.
Nice to meet you, Francesco. Welcome.
만나서 반갑습니다, 프란체스코 학생. 환영합니다.
I see that you selected a lesson about Walt Whitman and his famous poem,
월트 휘트먼과 그의 유명한 시에 관한 수업을 선택하신 것으로 알고 있습니다.
Oh, captain, my captain, a reading and writing class. Is that right?
"오, 선장님! 나의 선장님!" 읽기 및 쓰기 수업 말이죠. 맞습니까?
Yes, that is correct.
네, 맞습니다.
Okay, great.
네, 좋습니다.
So I'll tell you a little bit about Abraham Lincoln.
그럼 에이브러햄 링컨에 대해 조금 말씀드리겠습니다.
You've probably heard of honest Abe before he was the 16th US president.
아마 '정직한 에이브'라는 별명은 들어보셨을 겁니다. 그는 미국의 제16대 대통령이었습니다.
He was assassinated in 1865.
그는 1865년에 암살당했습니다.
You might compare him to another famous leader. Do you know who this guy is?
그를 다른 유명한 지도자와 비교해 볼 수도 있겠습니다. 이분이 누구인지 아시겠어요?
Yes, Francisco Morazán.
네, 프란시스코 모라산입니다.
Francisco Morazán. Okay, so they're not the same, but they are very popular presidents, right?
프란시스코 모라산이요. 네, 두 분이 같지는 않지만, 매우 인기 있는 대통령들이었죠, 그렇죠?
Correct. Yes.
맞습니다. 네.
So this question for us is what makes a good leader?
그래서 우리가 던져볼 질문은 '무엇이 좋은 지도자를 만드는가?'입니다.
Take a minute to think about it, and then you can share with me and talk about this.
잠시 생각해 보시고, 저와 함께 의견을 나눠 이야기해 보도록 하죠.
What makes a good leader in your opinion?
프란체스코 학생의 생각에는 무엇이 좋은 지도자를 만든다고 보십니까?
Okay.
네.
Do you want me to write it down or can I just start?
적어 내려가야 할까요, 아니면 바로 시작해도 될까요?
Yeah, you can.
네, 바로 말씀하셔도 됩니다.
I think it's not only someone that inspires, but also knows when to take action.
제 생각에는 영감을 주는 사람일 뿐만 아니라, 언제 행동을 취해야 하는지 아는 사람이라고 생각합니다.
Okay.
알겠습니다.
Alright, agreed. Somebody with initiative, right?
네, 동의합니다. 주도력을 가진 사람이겠죠, 그렇죠?
Yes, absolutely.
네, 물론입니다.
I think both of these leaders were leaders who inspired others and took a great initiative.
제 생각에 이 두 지도자 모두 다른 사람들에게 영감을 주고 엄청난 주도력을 발휘한 지도자들이었습니다.
I would agree.
동의합니다.
Both of them were involved with some great liberal reforms as well.
두 분 모두 몇몇 위대한 자유주의적 개혁에도 관여했습니다.
Alright, so we have a list of things that can help us to improve our English in particular reading and writing and speaking too since we'll be having a conversation throughout the entire lesson.
자, 여기에는 우리의 영어 실력, 특히 읽기와 쓰기, 그리고 전체 수업 동안 대화를 나눌 것이므로 말하기 능력까지 향상시키는 데 도움이 될 수 있는 목록이 있습니다.
These are our class objectives.
이것이 우리 수업의 목표입니다.
Can you read the class objectives starting with this one here?
여기 첫 번째 것부터 시작해서 수업 목표를 읽어주시겠어요?
Yes, identify and explain the historical context of O-Captain, My Captain.
네, "오, 선장님! 나의 선장님!"의 역사적 배경을 파악하고 설명하기.
Define key vocabulary.
주요 어휘 정의하기.
For example,
예를 들면,
?legy,
엘..레지?
keel, rack,
용골, 모진 풍파,
or is it
아니면
elegy.
엘레지입니다.
And identify and extend it metaphor within the poem.
그리고 시 내부의 확장 은유를 파악하고 설명하기.
Analyze the extended metaphor, explaining what the captain, ship, fearful trip and prize represent.
확장 은유를 분석하여 선장, 배, 두려운 여정, 그리고 전리품이 무엇을 나타내는지 설명하기.
Discuss the tone of the poem as it relates to grief and admiration.
슬픔과 존경심과 관련하여 시의 분위기를 토론하기.
And express understanding of the poem through discussion and written responses.
그리고 토론과 작문 응답을 통해 시에 대한 이해를 표현하기.
Okay.
네.
Oh, and connect the poem's themes of loss, leadership, and national strategy to broader concepts of freedom.
아, 그리고 시의 주제인 상실, 리더십, 그리고 국가적 시련을 더 넓은 자유의 개념과 연결하기.
Is it a freedom?
자유인가요?
Like freedom.
자유 같은 거요.
Yeah.
네.
Oh, like freedom.
아, 자유 같은 거군요.
Alright, so we have a lot that we can do.
자, 우리가 할 수 있는 일이 많습니다.
We might not have time to do all of this, but certainly there is a lot to digest about this poem.
이 모든 것을 다 할 시간이 없을 수도 있지만, 분명 이 시에 대해 음미할 부분이 많습니다.
And well, well, Whitman and historical context here.
그리고 음, 월트 휘트먼과 여기의 역사적 배경에 대해서도요.
The vocabulary can be a little bit antiquated because it's, it was written in 1865 right after the assassination of Abraham Lincoln.
어휘가 다소 고풍스러울 수 있습니다. 왜냐하면 이 시는 에이브러햄 링컨 암살 직후인 1865년에 쓰였기 때문입니다.
So I just want you to keep that in mind as we read this.
그러니 이 시를 읽을 때 그 점을 염두에 두시기 바랍니다.
There's a context to this poem.
이 시에는 배경이 있습니다.
And maybe it's talking about something a little deeper.
그리고 아마도 좀 더 깊은 무언가에 대해 이야기하고 있을지도 모릅니다.
So when we say extended metaphor, you know, a metaphor is when A is B.
그래서 우리가 확장 은유라고 할 때, 아시다시피 은유는 A가 B인 경우를 말합니다.
But an extended metaphor is when maybe a whole paragraph or text is standing for something.
하지만 확장 은유는 어쩌면 한 문단 전체나 글 전체가 무언가를 상징하는 경우를 말합니다.
Okay.
네.
So some historical context here.
자, 여기 약간의 역사적 배경이 있습니다.
But first here, what do you know about the American Civil War or Abraham Lincoln?
하지만 먼저, 미국 남북전쟁이나 에이브러햄 링컨에 대해 무엇을 알고 계신가요?
Oh, I know, I know the nickname honest Abe.
아, '정직한 에이브'라는 별명은 알고 있습니다.
(The) American Civil War was specifically regarding slavery.
미국 남북전쟁은 특히 노예제와 관련이 있었죠.
If I'm not mistaken, correct?
제가 틀리지 않았다면, 맞나요?
Yes.
네.
North and the South.
북부와 남부 사이의 전쟁이었고요.
And then Abraham Lincoln.
그리고 에이브러햄 링컨은...
Well, you said the 16th president, but I think there's something.
음, 제16대 대통령이라고 하셨는데, 제 생각엔 뭔가...
I think there was a very important decision he took and I can't quite remember it.
그가 내린 매우 중요한 결정이 있었던 것 같은데, 정확히 기억이 나질 않네요.
Something that he's really known about.
그가 정말로 유명하게 된 계기가 된 무언가가요.
The emancipation proclamation.
노예 해방 선언 말씀이시군요.
Yeah.
네.
All right.
그렇습니다.
Excellent.
훌륭합니다.
So you know some about the American Civil War in the context of this poem.
미국 남북전쟁과 이 시의 배경에 대해 어느 정도 알고 계시는군요.
How important this was the Civil War in the United States.
미국에서 남북전쟁이 얼마나 중요했는지 아실 겁니다.
Didn't just affect the United States had a cascade effect to other countries.
단순히 미국에만 영향을 미친 것이 아니라 다른 나라들에도 연쇄적인 파급 효과를 가져왔습니다.
And really changed a lot of attitudes.
그리고 정말로 많은 태도를 변화시켰습니다.
And it wasn't over at the end of the Civil War.
그리고 남북전쟁이 끝났다고 해서 모든 것이 끝난 것은 아니었습니다.
And it's still not over.
그리고 여전히 끝나지 않았습니다.
Really, we still fight with inequality.
정말로, 우리는 여전히 불평등과 싸우고 있습니다.
We still fight with issues related to slavery around the world.
우리는 여전히 전 세계적으로 노예제와 관련된 문제들과 싸우고 있습니다.
And this question about what it really means to be free.
그리고 진정으로 자유롭다는 것이 무엇을 의미하는지에 대한 이 질문도요.
And it's still an uphill battle.
그리고 그것은 여전히 힘겨운 싸움입니다.
So we what Whitman wrote, oh, captain, my captain in 1865 shortly after two major events here.
그래서 월트 휘트먼은 1865년에 "오, 선장님! 나의 선장님!"을 썼는데, 바로 두 가지 주요 사건 직후였습니다.
Can you read this part for us?
이 부분을 읽어주시겠어요?
Of course, the end of the Civil War, which lasted from 1861 to 1865.
물론입니다. 1861년부터 1865년까지 지속된 남북전쟁의 종결.
A rural conflict that divided the nation.
국가를 분열시킨 잔혹한 분쟁이었습니다.
And the assassination of President Abraham Abraham Lincoln in April 1865 just days after the Confederates surrender.
그리고 1865년 4월 에이브러햄 링컨 대통령의 암살은 남부 연합이 항복한 지 불과 며칠 후였습니다.
Lincoln was seen by many as the captain who had steered the nation.
링컨은 많은 사람들에게 국가라는 배를 조종한 선장으로 여겨졌습니다.
the ship... through the fearful trip of the war.
그 배는... 전쟁이라는 두려운 여정을 헤쳐 나왔습니다.
So we see an example of a metaphor already the nation as the ship he steered it he was the captain.
그래서 우리는 이미 은유의 한 예를 볼 수 있습니다. 국가를 배로, 그가 배를 조종했고, 그가 선장이었던 것이죠.
in this poem that we're going to read.
우리가 읽게 될 이 시에서 말입니다.
So that we have another colored picture of Abraham Lincoln.
여기 에이브러햄 링컨의 또 다른 컬러 사진이 있습니다.
I just think it's cool that they can put color to old pictures now.
요즘 옛날 사진에 색을 입힐 수 있다는 게 정말 멋지다고 생각합니다.
And it makes it look real.
그리고 실제처럼 보이게 만들죠.
And a scene from something that you would have seen in the newspaper.
그리고 이것은 신문에서 봤을 법한 장면입니다.
So Abraham Lincoln was in a theater when he was shot and assassinated.
에이브러햄 링컨은 극장에서 총에 맞아 암살당했습니다.
All right.
네.
So here we have some terms that we need to know.
자, 여기 우리가 알아야 할 몇 가지 용어들이 있습니다.
And you might hesitate with some of these vocabulary words.
이 어휘들 중 일부는 조금 망설여질 수도 있습니다.
They're a little difficult.
조금 어렵거든요.
So we have lyric, elegy, metaphor and extended metaphor.
서정시, 엘레지, 은유, 그리고 확장 은유가 있습니다.
Lyric poetry is poetry that expresses personal emotions or feelings.
서정시는 개인적인 감정이나 느낌을 표현하는 시입니다.
It's typically spoken in the first person.
일반적으로 1인칭으로 이야기됩니다.
So the poem that we're about to read is lyric poetry.
그래서 우리가 곧 읽을 시는 서정시입니다.
And this one, remember the pronunciation, elegy, could you read this for us?
그리고 이것, 발음을 기억하세요, 엘레지. 이 부분을 읽어주시겠어요?
Yes.
네.
A poem of serious reflection, typically a lament for the dead.
진지한 성찰을 담은 시로, 일반적으로 죽은 이를 애도하는 노래입니다.
Oh, captain, my captain is an elegy for Abraham Lincoln.
"오, 선장님! 나의 선장님!"은 에이브러햄 링컨을 위한 엘레지입니다.
All right.
그렇습니다.
So we're talking about someone a captain who was killed.
그래서 우리는 살해된 선장에 대해 이야기하고 있는 것입니다.
And so the poem is really deep.
그래서 이 시는 정말 깊이가 있습니다.
And it's a little dark in that sense.
그리고 그런 의미에서 약간 어둡기도 합니다.
You have to imagine the feeling at the end of a war.
전쟁이 끝났을 때의 감정을 상상해 보셔야 합니다.
The feeling at the end of the war is one of relief.
전쟁이 끝났을 때의 감정은 안도감일 수 있습니다.
you could imagine, but also great sadness.
안도감도 있었겠지만, 동시에 큰 슬픔도 있었을 것입니다.
You can't bring back the lives that were lost.
잃어버린 생명들을 되돌릴 수는 없습니다.
You can't undo what was done.
일어난 일을 되돌릴 수는 없습니다.
What was done was done.
일어난 일은 이미 일어난 일입니다.
We have a metaphor, a figure of speech in which a word or phrase is applied.
은유가 있습니다. 단어나 구가 적용되는 화법이죠.
So when one thing is another, and then this extension of that, the extended metaphor.
즉, 한 가지가 다른 것일 때, 그리고 그것의 확장인 확장 은유가 있습니다.
Could you read this one for us?
이 부분을 읽어주시겠어요?
Yes.
네.
A metaphor that is developed over several lines of writing or even throughout an entire work.
여러 줄의 글이나 작품 전체에 걸쳐 전개되는 은유입니다.
Great.
훌륭합니다.
So here's the first reading.
자, 첫 번째 낭독입니다.
I'll read this first one for you.
이 첫 부분은 제가 읽겠습니다.
I want you to listen to the way that this sounds.
이것이 어떻게 들리는지 귀 기울여 들어보시기 바랍니다.
While follow eyes and steady keel.
모두의 시선이 안정된 용골을 따르는 동안,
The vessel grim and daring.
배는 암울하고도 대담하게 나아가네.
But oh, heart, heart, heart.
하지만 오, 심장아, 심장아, 심장아!
Oh, the bleeding drops of red.
오, 흐르는 붉은 핏방울이여,
Where on the deck, my captain lies, fallen cold and dead.
나의 선장님이 갑판 위에 쓰러져 있네, 차갑고 싸늘하게.
So we have this image of a ship with a keel.
그래서 우리는 용골이 있는 배의 이미지를 보게 됩니다.
So certain part of the ship, right?
배의 특정 부분이죠, 그렇죠?
The vessel grim and daring.
암울하고 대담한 배.
You see this dark ship entering.
이 어두운 배가 들어오는 것을 보게 됩니다.